<ideaollogy><overall># Designing MLSpec

## Executive summary

MLSpec should be designed as a **case-centric provenance and validity layer for ML experimentation**, not as another training framework, scheduler, notebook system, or generic experiment tracker. The strongest foundation is to combine the provenance core of ţłÇentityţłé["other","PROV","W3C provenance data model"]ţłü from the ţłÇentityţłé["organization","World Wide Web Consortium","web standards organization"]ţłü, the adaptive ÔÇťcase fileÔÇŁ model of ţłÇentityţłé["other","CMMN","Case Management Model and Notation standard"]ţłü from the ţłÇentityţłé["organization","Object Management Group","standards consortium"]ţłü, run/artifact telemetry from ţłÇentityţłé["software","MLflow","machine learning experiment tracking platform"]ţłü, orchestration metadata from ţłÇentityţłé["software","Kubeflow","Kubernetes-native ML workflow platform"]ţłü, exploratory-history lessons from ţłÇentityţłé["software","VisTrails","scientific workflow and provenance management system"]ţłü, and agent-trace extensions from PROV-AGENT. PROV supplies the minimal classes and relations; CMMN supplies adaptive case progression; MLflow and Kubeflow supply execution metadata; VisTrails shows the value of retaining full exploratory history; and PROV-AGENT shows that prompts, responses, decisions, and downstream effects must become first-class provenance when agents are involved. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn15view1ţłéturn7view2ţłéturn23view0ţłéturn7view3ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn18view0ţłéturn18view3ţłü

The right abstraction is therefore: **MLSpec = protocol + run provenance + compute-aware evidence grading + decision gating + agent traceability**. The system should keep a minimal, queryable internal model, then render human-facing projections such as markdown, YAML, or HTML. That recommendation is supported by the scientific-workflow literature, which treats provenance as queryable lineage and warns that provenance can become large enough to require selective capture, and by MLflow/Kubeflow, which both center queryable run/metadata stores rather than free-form narrative files. ţłÇciteţłéturn16view2ţłéturn12view2ţłéturn12view4ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn14view1ţłü

The minimal kernel should be small: **Actor, Case, Protocol, Run, Artifact, MetricResult, Deviation, Evidence, Claim, Decision, and ActionLog**. Everything else should be projections or typed substructures. In PROV terms, Protocol is a plan-like entity; Run and ActionLog are activities; Actor is an agent; Artifact, MetricResult, Evidence, Claim, Decision, and Deviation are entities. In CMMN terms, Case is the evolving case file root, while readiness, execution, and resolution are lifecycle states gated by sentries and completion criteria. ţłÇciteţłéturn25view0ţłéturn25view1ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn11view0ţłéturn11view2ţłü

The distinctive part of MLSpec should be its **compute-aware evidence rubric**. The ţłÇentityţłé["event","NeurIPS","machine learning conference"]ţłü checklist and subsequent reproducibility work emphasize recording exact run counts, hyperparameters, metrics, runtime or energy cost, computing infrastructure, and variation across runs; the broader reproducibility literature explicitly recommends multiple random seeds and reporting variance, while also noting that computational-resource limits are a major barrier to reproducibility. That means MLSpec should not treat ÔÇťa run happenedÔÇŁ as enough. Instead it should record whether the observed run consumed enough of the intended resource envelopeÔÇöGPU-hours, data fraction, seeds, epochs, wall-clock timeÔÇöto justify the claim being made. ţłÇciteţłéturn9view1ţłéturn7view8ţłéturn21view0ţłü

Design and evaluation should follow **Design Science Research**: build an artifact, evaluate it rigorously against relevant failures, iterate as a search process, and communicate both the artifact and the method. For MLSpec, that means failure-driven modeling, adversarial fixtures, and audits that block unsupported conclusions automatically. ţłÇciteţłéturn17view0ţłétun17view1ţłéturn17view2ţłéturn17view3ţłéturn17view4ţłü

| MLSpec should be | MLSpec should not be |
|---|---|
| A local-first control plane for protocol, evidence, and decisions | A Kubernetes-first platform |
| A provenance graph for runs, artifacts, and agent actions | A tracker that only logs metrics |
| A decision gate that limits what conclusions are allowed | A scheduler or trainer |
| A thin layer with adapters into trackers/orchestrators | A heavyweight MLOps stack |

The table above is the central design conclusion of the source review and is especially consistent with the separation of concerns visible in PROV, CMMN, MLflow, Kubeflow, VisTrails, and PROV-AGENT. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn7view2ţłéturn7view3ţłéturn15view1ţłéturn18view0ţłü

## What existing systems already solve

The systems below already solve large parts of the problem, but none of them solve the specific MLSpec wedge: **turning ML runs and agent actions into bounded, auditable experimental conclusions**. The matrix is a synthesis of the official documentation and primary papers cited after the table. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn11view0ţłéturn11view2ţłéturn7view2ţłéturn23view0ţłéturn7view3ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn14view1ţłéturn14view2ţłéturn15view1ţłéturn18view0ţłéturn18view3ţłü

| Source/system | Native strengths | Important gaps for MLSpec | Best reuse inside MLSpec |
|---|---|---|---|
| PROV | Minimal, interoperable provenance core: Entity, Activity, Agent; Used, WasGeneratedBy, WasDerivedFrom, WasAttributedTo, WasAssociatedWith; plans represented as entities | No ML-specific validity rules, no evidence grading, no resource semantics beyond whatever the application adds | Use as the ontology substrate and graph vocabulary |
| CMMN | Case-centric modeling for unpredictable, knowledge-worker-driven work; case file; sentry-gated activation; explicit lifecycle states for tasks/stages | No ML metrics, no statistical validity, no run-resource semantics | Use for case/state/lifecycle ideas, not for notation adoption |
| MLflow | Strong run-centric logging of parameters, code versions, metrics, artifacts; experiment grouping; run search; local default storage; system metrics for CPU/GPU/memory/network/disk | No protocol contract, no claim/decision semantics, no evidence-grade gating | Use as optional run/artifact/system-metrics backend |
| Kubeflow | Strong orchestration layer: DAG pipelines on Kubernetes, immutable/self-contained runs, artifact passing, metadata store, lineage graph | Heavy infrastructure footprint; workflow execution focus; weak epistemic layer | Use as optional orchestrator/lineage source when infra exists |
| VisTrails | Captures complete history of workflows, executions, and results; version diff/replay; strong exploratory provenance | Not agent-native, not ML-decision-focused, not built around modern tracker/orchestrator integration | Reuse its ÔÇťkeep the exploratory trailÔÇŁ philosophy |
| PROV-AGENT | Brings prompts, responses, model invocations, decisions, and downstream impact into the provenance graph | Early and agent-centric; does not by itself solve ML evidence grading or decision policy | Use for ActionLog and agent-facing provenance requirements |

The synthesis is straightforward: PROV supplies the **graph grammar**, CMMN supplies the **adaptive case shell**, MLflow and Kubeflow supply **execution exhaust**, VisTrails supplies **history retention**, and PROV-AGENT supplies **agent traceability**. MLSpecÔÇÖs own contribution should sit on top of them as the **validity and decision layer**. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn11view0ţłéturn7view2ţłéturn23view0ţłéturn7view3ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn15view1ţłéturn18view0ţłéturn18view3ţłü

That same source mix also explains why MLSpec should stay lightweight. Scientific-workflow provenance is valuable because it makes results queryable, debuggable, and reproducible, but the literature also warns that provenance volume can exceed the original data and must therefore be selective. Kubeflow is inherently cluster- and orchestration-oriented; MLflow is more run-centric and can default to a local `mlruns` directory. The best reading is that MLSpec should keep only the metadata required to prevent invalid conclusions, while leaving heavy artifact storage and large-scale execution to external tools. ţłÇciteţłéturn16view2ţłéturn14view1ţłéturn12view3ţłéturn12view4ţłü

## Proposed MLSpec semantic kernel

A strong v0 should use a **queryable source of truth**ÔÇöSQLite or append-only JSONL are reasonable defaultsÔÇöand render markdown/YAML reports as projections. That is more robust than treating markdown as the data model, because the central source patterns here are graphs, queries, and lineage joins, not just narrative notes. PROV is explicitly graph-based; scientific-workflow provenance is queried and visualized; MLflow and Kubeflow both expose queryable run and metadata concepts; and VisTrails emphasizes replayable history rather than only current-state documents. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn16view2ţłéturn12view2ţłéturn12view4ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn15view1ţłü

Use the following scalar conventions in the kernel: `ID`, `Ref<T>`, `Enum[...]`, `Timestamp`, `URI`, `Digest`, `Map<String,Scalar>`, and a reusable `ResourceBudget = {gpu_hours: float, wallclock_hours: float, data_fraction: float[0,1], seeds: int, epochs: int, peak_vram_gb?: float, accelerator_type?: string}`. This schema is a proposed synthesis, derived from PROVÔÇÖs entity/activity/agent core, CMMNÔÇÖs case/lifecycle framing, MLflowÔÇÖs run/experiment/artifact model, KubeflowÔÇÖs run/artifact/metadata concepts, and the reproducibility checklistÔÇÖs emphasis on exact runs, metrics, infrastructure, and runtime/energy reporting. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn7view2ţłéturn23view0ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn14view2ţłéturn9view1ţłü

| Noun | Minimal fields and types | Why it should be first-class |
|---|---|---|
| `Actor` | `id`, `kind: Enum[human, agent, service]`, `name`, `version?`, `provider?` | Responsibility and traceability |
| `Case` | `id`, `question`, `status: Enum[proposed, ready, running, observed, resolved, reopened, archived]`, `active_protocol_ref`, `owner_refs`, `created_at`, `tags` | Adaptive experiment root / case file |
| `Protocol` | `id`, `case_ref`, `version`, `objective`, `baseline_spec`, `dataset_specs`, `metric_specs`, `planned_resources: ResourceBudget`, `min_decision_grade`, `acceptance_rule`, `locked_at?` | Experimental contract; PROV-like plan |
| `Run` | `id`, `case_ref`, `protocol_ref`, `run_kind: Enum[smoke, proxy, full, replication]`, `status: Enum[planned, queued, running, completed, failed, aborted]`, `tracker_refs`, `started_at`, `ended_at`, `command`, `commit_hash`, `environment_digest`, `input_artifact_refs`, `output_artifact_refs`, `actual_resources: ResourceBudget`, `interrupt_reason?` | Executed attempt |
| `Artifact` | `id`, `kind: Enum[code, config, dataset, split_manifest, checkpoint, log, report, prompt, response, model, metrics_blob]`, `uri`, `digest`, `produced_by_run_ref?`, `metadata` | Immutable lineage node |
| `MetricResult` | `id`, `run_ref`, `name`, `split`, `value`, `direction`, `aggregation`, `dispersion?`, `seed?`, `evaluator_artifact_ref` | Comparison-ready metric atom |
| `Deviation` | `id`, `run_ref`, `category`, `severity: Enum[minor, material, fatal]`, `description`, `declared_by_actor_ref`, `impact: Enum[none, weakens, invalidates]`, `resolved: bool` | Captures protocol drift explicitly |
| `Evidence` | `id`, `case_ref`, `run_refs`, `metric_result_refs`, `artifact_refs`, `deviation_refs`, `grade: Enum[smoke, proxy, partial, decision_grade, replicated, invalid]`, `scope`, `protocol_satisfied: Enum[yes, partial, no]`, `summary` | Converts raw run exhaust into classified support |
| `Claim` | `id`, `case_ref`, `statement`, `scope`, `comparator`, `expected_direction?`, `evidence_refs` | What is actually being asserted |
| `Decision` | `id`, `case_ref`, `claim_ref`, `status: Enum[accept, reject, inconclusive, rerun, archive]`, `rationale`, `evidence_refs`, `decided_by_actor_ref`, `decided_at` | Final allowed conclusion |
| `ActionLog` | `id`, `actor_ref`, `action_type`, `target_ref`, `parent_action_ref?`, `prompt_artifact_ref?`, `command?`, `started_at`, `ended_at`, `stdout_artifact_ref?`, `stderr_artifact_ref?` | Agent/human execution trace |

If the system must be reduced further for a first prototype, the least harmful compression is to nest `MetricResult` inside `Evidence` and `ActionLog` inside `Run.events`; the least safe compression is to collapse `Protocol`, `Evidence`, `Claim`, and `Decision`, because those are exactly the layers that separate ÔÇťwhat happenedÔÇŁ from ÔÇťwhat is allowed to be concluded.ÔÇŁ That separation is consistent with PROVÔÇÖs distinction between activities, entities, agents, and plans, with CMMNÔÇÖs case/lifecycle separation, and with reproducibility guidance that distinguishes procedure, evaluation, and reporting. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn7view1ţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłü

The ontology below shows the recommended provenance spine, with explicit mapping back to PROV concepts. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn25view0ţłéturn18view3ţłü

```mermaid
flowchart LR
  Actor{{Actor\nprov:Agent}}
  Action[ActionLog\nprov:Activity]
  Case[(Case)]
  Protocol[[Protocol\nprov:Plan]]
  Run[Run\nprov:Activity]
  Artifact[(Artifact\nprov:Entity)]
  Metric[(MetricResult\nprov:Entity)]
  Deviation[(Deviation\nprov:Entity)]
  Evidence[(Evidence\nprov:Entity)]
  Claim[(Claim\nprov:Entity)]
  Decision[(Decision\nprov:Entity)]

  Case -->|has current| Protocol
  Actor -->|performs| Action
  Action -->|creates/updates| Case
  Action -->|creates/updates| Protocol
  Protocol -->|governs| Run
  Run -->|uses| Artifact
  Run -->|generates| Artifact
  Run -->|generates| Metric
  Run -->|records| Deviation
  Evidence -->|cites| Run
  Evidence -->|cites| Metric
  Evidence -->|cites| Artifact
  Evidence -->|accounts for| Deviation
  Claim -->|supported/refuted by| Evidence
  Decision -->|resolves| Claim
  Decision -->|must cite| Evidence
```

The state model should likewise be explicit. CMMN is helpful here because it models work that becomes available, is enabled or activated, can fail or terminate, and only completes when completion conditions are satisfied; Kubeflow and MLflow both treat runs as concrete execution records that can be queried and inspected. MLSpec should therefore use lifecycle gates that are stricter than ÔÇťartifact exists.ÔÇŁ ţłÇciteţłéturn11view2ţłéturn14view1ţłéturn12view2ţłü

```mermaid
stateDiagram-v2
  [*] --> Planned
  Planned --> Running: run_started
  Running --> Completed: success
  Running --> Failed: exception
  Running --> Aborted: stop

  Completed --> Smoke: evidence_classified
  Completed --> Proxy: evidence_classified
  Completed --> Partial: evidence_classified
  Completed --> DecisionGrade: evidence_classified
  Completed --> Replicated: evidence_classified

  Failed --> Invalid: evidence_classified
  Aborted --> Invalid: evidence_classified

  Smoke --> Inconclusive: decide
  Proxy --> Inconclusive: decide
  Partial --> Inconclusive: decide
  Partial --> NeedsRerun: decide
  DecisionGrade --> Accept: decide_positive
  DecisionGrade --> Reject: decide_negative
  Replicated --> Accept: decide_positive
  Replicated --> Reject: decide_negative
  Invalid --> NeedsRerun: decide
```

| Object | States | Gate to move forward | Key invariant |
|---|---|---|---|
| `Case` | proposed Ôćĺ ready Ôćĺ running Ôćĺ observed Ôćĺ resolved Ôćĺ reopened/archive | protocol lock, at least one run, evidence recorded, decision issued | case cannot be `ready` without an active protocol |
| `Run` | planned Ôćĺ queued Ôćĺ running Ôćĺ completed / failed / aborted | command started, tracker id attached, completion status known | protocol version must be immutable once run starts |
| `Evidence` | unclassified Ôćĺ smoke / proxy / partial / decision_grade / replicated / invalid | run resources, comparator validity, deviations, evaluation completeness | evidence grade is about **strength**, not whether the result is positive or negative |
| `Decision` | pending Ôćĺ accept / reject / inconclusive / rerun / archive | cited evidence has minimum required grade and matching scope | no decision may exist without explicit evidence references |

The non-negotiable invariants should be simple and machine-checkable: a decision must cite evidence; evidence must cite observed runs rather than planned work; metric comparisons require identical split and evaluator definitions; any material unresolved deviation caps evidence at `partial`; any fatal deviation or lineage hole makes evidence `invalid`; and `decision_grade` requires actual resource reporting, not just intended budget. Those invariants are direct answers to the failure patterns surfaced by the provenance, workflow, and reproducibility sources. ţłÇciteţłéturn16view2ţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłéturn18view0ţłü

## Failure taxonomy and required provenance

The most reliable way to derive MLSpec is to derive it **from failure**. The literature supports this direction indirectly but strongly: provenance exists to answer lineage questions and aid debugging; design-science treats artifact improvement as an iterative search-and-evaluation process; reproducibility guidance emphasizes under-specification, metric ambiguity, incomplete reporting, randomness, and hidden compute constraints as recurring failure sources. The table below turns that into an operational failure taxonomy for MLSpec. ţłÇciteţłéturn16view2ţłéturn17view2ţłéturn17view4ţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłü

| Failure category | Typical examples | Required provenance fields | Minimum automated gate |
|---|---|---|---|
| Identity and versioning holes | orphan checkpoint; config edited after run; result copied without origin | `artifact.digest`, `produced_by_run_ref`, `commit_hash`, `config_digest`, `created_at` | reject orphan or mutable evidence |
| Data lineage and split integrity | wrong eval split; train/test leakage; changed preprocessing | `dataset_digest`, `split_manifest_digest`, `preprocessing_artifact_ref`, `dataset_version`, `row_count` | forbid comparison if split/preprocessing digests differ |
| Metric and evaluator mismatch | same metric name, different script or threshold; aggregate mismatch | `metric_name`, `direction`, `aggregation`, `evaluator_artifact_ref`, `evaluator_digest`, `split` | forbid comparison if evaluator digests differ |
| Protocol drift | fewer epochs than planned; different augmentation; manual tweak not logged | `protocol_ref`, `protocol_version`, `deviation_refs`, `severity`, `impact`, `approved_override?` | unresolved material deviation caps evidence below decision-grade |
| Resource under-run or interruption | 10% data treated as final; fewer seeds; OOM; early stop; reduced resolution proxy | `actual_resources`, `interrupt_reason`, `resume_chain`, `gpu_hours`, `data_fraction`, `epochs`, `seeds` | compute ratio and interruption status set max evidence grade |
| Statistical weakness and cherry-picking | single-seed superiority claim; best-of-n run selected silently; no variance | `seed_list`, `n_runs`, `aggregation`, `dispersion`, `selection_rule`, `confidence_interval?` | no decision-grade without required run count and variation metadata |
| Comparator or baseline invalidity | missing baseline; incomparable baseline; baseline run used different split or metric | `baseline_run_refs`, `comparator_type`, `shared_split_manifest`, `shared_metric_spec`, `shared_budget_class` | comparison claims require matched baseline metadata |
| Environment and infrastructure mismatch | CUDA/driver drift; different container; hardware nondeterminism hidden | `environment_digest`, `container_image_digest`, `dependency_lock_digest`, `accelerator_type`, `driver_versions` | environment diff emits warning or blocks strict comparability |
| Agent traceability failure | agent cites planned run as evidence; invents result from logs; hides failed command | `actor_ref`, `action_logs`, `prompt_artifact_ref`, `command`, `stdout/stderr_artifacts`, `decision.evidence_refs` | planned work cannot be evidence; decisions require trace-complete action logs |

Two design implications matter most. First, most failures are prevented by **recording digests and references**, not by storing huge blobs in the core store. Second, a lightweight system should store canonical URIs and hashes for large artifacts while keeping the actual artifacts in filesystem/object storage or external trackers. That is exactly the right response to the scientific-workflow finding that provenance data can exceed the size of the original data and therefore must be captured selectively. ţłÇciteţłéturn16view2ţłü

A useful rule of thumb is: if a field cannot help answer either **ÔÇťwhat produced this?ÔÇŁ** or **ÔÇťwhat conclusion is allowed?ÔÇŁ**, it probably should not be in the kernel. That rule is consistent with PROVÔÇÖs focus on production/use/responsibility and with Design Science ResearchÔÇÖs emphasis on purposeful artifacts rather than arbitrarily complex representations. ţłÇciteţłéturn24view0ţłéturn17view0ţłü

## Compute-aware evidence, decisions, and audit

The evidence system should treat **resource consumption as part of epistemic strength**. That is not because bigger runs are always better, but because the primary sources repeatedly tie credibility to reporting exact runs, infrastructure, runtime or energy cost, and variance across runs, while also identifying compute limits as a practical reproducibility barrier. A lightweight MLSpec therefore needs a simple, default rubric that turns intended budget and observed budget into a cap on what can be claimed. ţłÇciteţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłü

The recommended default is to compare observed resources against the protocol target and use the **minimum completeness ratio** across the key dimensions: `gpu_hours`, `data_fraction`, `epochs`, and `seeds`. Domain-specific protocols can override the exact thresholds, but the defaults below are a strong v0. This is a proposed rubric, informed by reproducibility and reporting guidance rather than copied from a single existing standard. ţłÇciteţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłü

| Evidence grade | Default resource profile | Additional conditions | What it can justify |
|---|---|---|---|
| `smoke` | `< 0.10` of planned GPU-hours **or** no real evaluation **or** dry-run/sanity-only | may have no valid comparator | wiring, shape, instrumentation, obvious crash/no-crash facts |
| `proxy` | `0.10ÔÇô0.30` of planned compute **or** reduced data/resolution/task proxy | comparator helpful but not required | ÔÇťworth a full run,ÔÇŁ ÔÇťlikely broken,ÔÇŁ ÔÇťdirectionally promisingÔÇŁ |
| `partial` | `0.30ÔÇô0.99` of planned compute **or** full compute with missing baseline / missing variance / unresolved material deviation | split and metric should still be explicit | bounded, preliminary claims under a narrow stated scope |
| `decision_grade` | `>= 1.00` of required compute envelope on full intended split/data/epochs with required seeds | matched baseline, evaluator digest, variance reporting, no unresolved material deviation | accept/reject **for this exact protocol scope** |
| `replicated` | `decision_grade` plus independent rerun, second seed bundle, or second environment/dataset slice specified by protocol | replication strategy explicit | stronger internal default changes; external communication candidate |
| `invalid` | any fatal deviation, lineage hole, noncomparable baseline, or leakage | none | only diagnostic conclusions and rerun requests |

The rubric should be interpreted conservatively. A positive full-budget result and a negative full-budget result are both `decision_grade` if they satisfy the protocol; evidence grade measures **strength**, not optimism. Conversely, a partial result that looks amazing is still partial if seeds, split, baseline, or resource envelope are insufficient. That distinction is exactly what is missing from pure run trackers. ţłÇciteţłéturn7view2ţłéturn14view1ţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłü

| Decision status | Minimum evidence requirement | Allowed conclusion form |
|---|---|---|
| `accept` | at least one cited `decision_grade` or `replicated` evidence item, all comparability checks pass | ÔÇťUnder protocol P.vN, on scope S, change X is accepted.ÔÇŁ |
| `reject` | same as `accept`, but the claim is negatively supported | ÔÇťUnder protocol P.vN, change X is rejected for scope S.ÔÇŁ |
| `inconclusive` | any `smoke`, `proxy`, or `partial` evidence, or conflicting evidence | ÔÇťObserved signal exists, but protocol-grade conclusion is not yet allowed.ÔÇŁ |
| `rerun` | `invalid` evidence, interrupted run, unresolved deviation, or insufficient run count | ÔÇťNo valid decision; rerun required with stated corrections.ÔÇŁ |
| `archive` | superseded case, abandoned line of inquiry, or administratively closed work | ÔÇťCase closed without a live decision target.ÔÇŁ |

The audit layer should query for invariant violations, not just missing files. The queries below are the minimum useful set for v0 and are directly aligned with the failure taxonomy. They are design recommendations rather than claims about existing tools. ţłÇciteţłéturn17view2ţłéturn18view0ţłü

| Audit query or check | Example logic | Failure caught |
|---|---|---|
| Unsupported decision | `decision.cited_evidence.grade < protocol.min_decision_grade` | overclaiming from weak evidence |
| Non-comparable comparison | split/evaluator/baseline digests differ across compared runs | invalid superiority claims |
| Underpowered ÔÇťfullÔÇŁ run | `run_kind='full'` but observed `data_fraction`, `epochs`, `seeds`, or `gpu_hours` below protocol minimum | proxy or partial run misrepresented as final |
| Orphan artifact | artifact has no `produced_by_run_ref` or no digest | untraceable outputs |
| Fatal deviation leakage | evidence grade Ôëą `decision_grade` but linked fatal/material deviation unresolved | invalid final decisions |
| Agent trace gap | decision by an agent lacks prompt/command/stdout-stderr references | unverifiable agent reasoning/execution |
| Future evidence | evidence cites a planned run or a run whose timestamps postdate the evidence record | fabricated or premature evidence |
| Cherry-pick detector | multiple sibling runs exist, but claim cites only best run and no `selection_rule` | silent selection bias |

In implementation terms, these checks should run at three moments: on `run end`, on `evidence classify`, and on `decide`. Early feedback catches missing metadata; late gating prevents epistemic overreach. That sequencing mirrors both workflow-lifecycle thinking and DSRÔÇÖs emphasis on evaluating artifact utility in realistic use. ţłÇciteţłéturn11view2ţłéturn17view2ţłü

## Agent-native interface and integrations

The agent interface should be **small, typed, and refusal-oriented**. PROV-AGENT is the clearest primary source here: in agentic workflows, the provenance system needs to capture prompts, responses, decisions, model invocations, and their downstream effects, because unsupported agent decisions can propagate errors across the rest of the workflow. MLSpec should therefore expose a CLI that makes valid transitions easy and invalid transitions hard. ţłÇciteţłéturn18view0ţłéturn18view3ţłü

A good v0 command surface is eight primitives:

| Primitive | Required inputs | Core invariant it enforces |
|---|---|---|
| `mlspec case create` | question, owner, tags | every experiment begins as an explicit case |
| `mlspec protocol lock` | case id, protocol body, baseline spec, metric specs, planned resources | runs cannot start against a mutable protocol |
| `mlspec run begin` | protocol id, command, tracker refs optional | captures commit/config/environment before execution |
| `mlspec run end` | run id, status, outputs, actual resources | no completed run without observed resources and artifacts |
| `mlspec evidence classify` | run id(s), metric refs, comparator refs | evidence grade cannot exceed resource/deviation cap |
| `mlspec claim draft` | case id, statement, scope, comparator | claims must be explicit and scoped |
| `mlspec decide` | claim id, evidence refs, rationale | no decision without valid cited evidence |
| `mlspec audit` | case or run scope | checks invariants and emits machine-readable failures |

The most important agent prompts are not long. They are structured preflight questions that force the agent to surface missing context instead of improvising. PROV-AGENT strongly supports making prompts and responses first-class artifacts, and the reproducibility sources strongly support requiring explicit protocol, metric, split, run-count, and infrastructure context. ţłÇciteţłéturn18view0ţłéturn18view3ţłéturn9view1ţłéturn21view0ţłü

```text
PRE-RUN GUARDRAIL
- What protocol version am I acting under?
- What exact command will run, and what commit/config/dataset digests will be attached?
- Is this run smoke, proxy, full, or replication?
- What evidence grade could this run support at most, even if metrics look good?

POST-RUN GUARDRAIL
- What was actually observed?
- What resources were actually consumed: GPU-hours, data fraction, epochs, seeds, wall-clock?
- What deviations occurred?
- Which artifacts and metric results were produced, with digests and evaluator versions?

DECISION GUARDRAIL
- Which evidence ids support this claim?
- Are split, metric, and baseline definitions comparable across cited runs?
- Does the maximum allowed evidence grade permit the requested decision?
- If any field is missing, return INSUFFICIENT_EVIDENCE instead of a conclusion.
```

MLflow and Kubeflow should be treated as adapters, not dependencies. The design below keeps MLSpec as the owner of protocol/evidence/decision semantics while pulling execution and telemetry from those backends when available. This separation matches the official docs: MLflow centers runs, experiments, artifacts, and system metrics; Kubeflow centers pipelines, runs, metadata stores, artifacts, and lineage graphs. ţłÇciteţłéturn7view2ţłéturn23view0ţłéturn14view1ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn14view2ţłü

| MLSpec concept | MLflow mapping | Kubeflow mapping | Recommended ownership |
|---|---|---|---|
| `Protocol` | experiment tags or run tags pointing to protocol version | pipeline spec/version or external reference in run metadata | owned by MLSpec |
| `Run` | MLflow run id, params, metrics, artifacts, start/end times | Kubeflow run id, pipeline/run graph, logs, output artifacts | observed from adapter, normalized by MLSpec |
| `Artifact` | artifact URI and metadata; model/checkpoint outputs | artifact URI, metadata, MLMD lineage nodes | canonical ref stored by MLSpec |
| `Actual resources` | system metrics: CPU/GPU/memory/network/disk; runtime | task status, telemetry/, node-level metadata where available via MLMD/cluster sources | normalized into `actual_resources` |
| `Evidence/Claim/Decision` | at most mirrored back as tags or artifacts | at most mirrored back as annotations | owned only by MLSpec |
| Search/audit | `search_runs` and experiment queries | metadata store and lineage graph traversal | cross-system audit issued from MLSpec |

The practical consequence is simple: MLSpec should ingest from external systems, but **never outsource claim validity to them**. MLflow can tell you what a run logged; Kubeflow can tell you what a pipeline executed; only MLSpec should tell you whether the resulting conclusion is allowed. ţłÇciteţłéturn12view2ţłéturn14view1ţłéturn14view0ţłü

## Evaluation plan and practical next steps

The evaluation method should explicitly follow Design Science Research: produce a viable artifact, solve a relevant problem, evaluate it rigorously, maintain rigor in construction and evaluation, and iterate as a search process. For MLSpec, that means a prototype is successful only if it blocks or flags invalid conclusions in adversarial experiment histories. ţłÇciteţłéturn17view0ţłéturn17view1ţłéturn17view2ţłéturn17view3ţłéturn17view4ţłü

A sensible minimal prototype can be built in five milestones:

| Milestone | Deliverable | Exit criterion |
|---|---|---|
| Kernel | typed schema for the 11 core nouns + validator | every object can be created, linked, and exported/imported |
| Gating | evidence classifier + decision matrix | impossible to accept/reject without cited evidence |
| Audit | invariant engine + machine-readable failures | all known fixture failures are caught |
| Adapter | MLflow ingest first, Kubeflow later | imported runs become normalized MLSpec runs |
| Agent shell | CLI + guardrail prompts + ActionLog capture | agent actions are replayable and attributable |

The initial fixture set should be deliberately adversarial:

| Fixture | Expected result |
|---|---|
| smoke run overclaimed as final | blocked at `evidence classify` or `decide` |
| wrong split manifest | comparison audit failure |
| evaluator script changed | comparison audit failure |
| baseline missing | claim cannot be comparative |
| config edited after run | lineage/immutability failure |
| partial-data run marked full | resource-grade downgrade |
| interrupted/OOM run treated as complete | invalid or rerun required |
| single-seed cherry-pick | no decision-grade evidence |
| orphan checkpoint imported from tracker | artifact audit failure |
| agent cites planned run as evidence | future-evidence failure |
| Kubeflow recurring run with changed parameters but same claim | protocol/version mismatch |
| MLflow run lacking commit or environment digest | lineage completeness failure |

The most important source list, in recommended reading order, is below. These are the sources with the highest design leverage for a first implementation, and they are intentionally biased toward primary or official material.

| Priority | Source | Why it matters first |
|---|---|---|
| highest | ţłÇurlţłéPROV-DMţłéturn1search0ţłü | Minimal provenance ontology and relations |
| highest | ţłÇurlţłéCMMN overviewţłéturn0search1ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéCMMN specificationţłéturn0search5ţłü | Case-file and lifecycle ideas for adaptive work |
| high | ţłÇurlţłéMLflow Tracking docsţłéturn0search2ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéMLflow System Metrics docsţłéturn22search0ţłü | What a modern lightweight tracker already gives you |
| high | ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow Pipelines docsţłéturn0search19ţłü, ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow run docsţłéturn13search12ţłü, and ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow ML Metadata docsţłéturn13search0ţłü | What orchestration and lineage look like when infra exists |
| high | ţłÇurlţłéVisTrailsţłéturn1search1ţłü | Why exploratory history should not be discarded |
| high | ţłÇurlţłéPROV-AGENT paperţłéturn2search0ţłü | How to make prompts, responses, and agent decisions first-class |
| medium | ţłÇurlţłéDesign Science in Information Systems Researchţłéturn1search14ţłü | Build/evaluate/iterate discipline for MLSpec itself |
| medium | ţłÇurlţłéMachine Learning Reproducibility Checklist v2.0ţłéturn6search2ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéJMLR report on the NeurIPS reproducibility programţłéturn6search18ţłü | Concrete reporting fields MLSpec should require |
| medium | ţłÇurlţłéScientific Workflows and Provenanceţłéturn1search7ţłü | Why provenance, scaling, adaptation, and selective capture matter |

Because infrastructure constraints are unspecified, the safest default is: **local-first, append-only metadata store; large artifacts external; MLflow adapter first; Kubeflow adapter optional; markdown exported as views**. That keeps the system lightweight while still matching the provenance, workflow, and reproducibility requirements that the source review makes hard to ignore. ţłÇciteţłéturn16view2ţłéturn12view4ţłéturn14view0ţłéturn14view1ţłü</overall><UX># MLSpec UX and Agent Control Design

## Executive summary

The right UX for MLSpec is **not** ÔÇťhumans use a strict CLI for everything.ÔÇŁ It is **chat-first, agent-mediated, policy-backed experimentation**: the human mostly speaks in high-level intents, the agent plans and executes bounded skills, and the CLI acts as the trusted control plane that records provenance, enforces invariants, and blocks unsupported conclusions. This design follows naturally from the provenance-first posture of the ţłÇurlţłéPROV-DM standardţłéturn1search0ţłü, the adaptive case-file model of ţłÇurlţłéCMMNţłéturn0search5ţłü, the run-centric telemetry model in ţłÇurlţłéMLflow docsţłéturn0search2ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéMLflow system metrics docsţłéturn22search0ţłü, the orchestration/lineage model in ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow docsţłéturn0search19ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow ML Metadata docsţłéturn13search0ţłü, the history-preserving philosophy of ţłÇurlţłéVisTrailsţłéturn1search1ţłü, and the explicit prompt/response/decision traceability proposed by ţłÇurlţłéPROV-AGENTţłéturn2search0ţłü. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn22search0ţłéturn0search19ţłéturn13search0ţłéturn1search1ţłéturn2search0ţłü

The key UX principle is **tiered rigidity**. Exploration should be fluid. Claims should not. A human should be able to jump around, try fast ideas, patch code, and run cheap checks with minimal ceremony; but crossing the boundaries into protocol-grade evidence and final decisions should invoke hard gates: immutable protocol version, captured code/config/data fingerprints, explicit resource accounting, evidence classification, and audit before acceptance or rejection. That split is strongly supported by the scientific-workflow literature, which values exploratory iteration and provenance retention, and by reproducibility guidance, which emphasizes exact reporting of runs, hyperparameters, compute, infrastructure, and variation across runs before drawing conclusions. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search1ţłéturn1search7ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłü

The separation of responsibility should therefore be sharp. The **human** supplies intent, priorities, risk tolerance, and final judgment on what matters. The **agent** plans, edits code, runs tests, proposes protocols, executes runs, and drafts claims through skills. The **CLI** owns state transitions, snapshots, audits, and policy enforcement. The **repo/tracker/orchestrator** owns code execution and artifact storage. That is the design that best accounts for agent weaknesses such as laziness, overclaiming, and weak long-term tracking, while still preserving the speed benefits of agentic work. ţłÇciteţłéturn2search0ţłéturn1search14ţłéturn6search2ţłü

## The core UX principle

MLSpec should be designed around one sentence:

> **Humans talk to the agent; the agent talks to the CLI; the CLI talks to the state model.**

That is the cleanest way to keep the human interface fluid while keeping the system itself trustworthy. It fits PROVÔÇÖs separation between agents, activities, and entities, and it fits CMMNÔÇÖs model of adaptive, knowledge-worker-driven cases rather than rigid assembly lines. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłü

```mermaid
flowchart LR
  H[Human intent]
  A[Agent planner/executor]
  S[Agent skills]
  C[MLSpec CLI control plane]
  M[(MLSpec state store)]
  R[Repo / tests / scripts]
  T[Tracker or orchestrator]
  D[Decision and audit output]

  H --> A
  A --> S
  S --> C
  S --> R
  R --> T
  C --> M
  T --> C
  R --> C
  M --> D
  C --> D
  D --> A
  A --> H
```

The implication is important: the CLI is **not** the main user experience. It is the **safety-critical API**. Most users should almost never touch it directly except to inspect state, recover from agent failure, or perform power-user debugging. The default experience should be a conversation with an agent that is visibly working inside a bounded protocol. That recommendation is a design synthesis, but it is grounded by the combination of adaptive case management in CMMN, provenance capture in PROV, and agent-trace requirements in PROV-AGENT. ţłÇciteţłéturn0search5ţłéturn1search0ţłéturn2search0ţłü

The right answer to ÔÇťhow rigid versus fluid should the workflow be?ÔÇŁ is therefore **neither fully rigid nor fully fluid**. It should be **fluid in exploration, rigid at boundary crossings**. That boundary-focused design mirrors the reporting and validation emphasis in the reproducibility checklist and the broader design-science view that artifacts should constrain exactly the parts of the process where failure is costly. ţłÇciteţłéturn6search2ţłéturn1search14ţłü

| Mode | Human experience | Agent freedom | CLI strictness | Allowed conclusions |
|---|---|---|---|---|
| Scratch | ÔÇťTry things fastÔÇŁ | high | low-to-medium | only local/debug conclusions |
| Structured | ÔÇťRun this as a real candidate experimentÔÇŁ | medium | high | bounded preliminary claims |
| Decision | ÔÇťTell me whether to accept/reject this changeÔÇŁ | low | very high | protocol-scoped accept/reject |

This three-mode structure is a design recommendation, but it directly operationalizes the difference between exploratory workflow history, protocol-strength evidence, and final decisions that the sources collectively point toward. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search1ţłéturn1search7ţłéturn6search2ţłü

## Division of responsibility

The most important implementation decision is to decide who is allowed to do what.

The table below is the recommended responsibility split. It is a synthesis built from the source set: PROV contributes responsibility and lineage, CMMN contributes case progression, MLflow and Kubeflow contribute run/artifact/system metadata patterns, and PROV-AGENT contributes explicit agent-action traces. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn22search0ţłéturn0search19ţłéturn13search0ţłéturn2search0ţłü

| Layer | Primary responsibility | Must never do |
|---|---|---|
| Human | set goals, approve priorities, choose tradeoffs, decide when ÔÇťgood enoughÔÇŁ matters | manually assert unsupported conclusions into MLSpec state |
| Agent | plan next actions, edit code, run skills, summarize evidence, request decisions | mutate MLSpec state by bypassing the CLI or silently ignore failed checks |
| CLI | create/update/query case state, bind runs to protocol versions, record fingerprints, classify evidence, enforce invariants, audit | make scientific judgments using free-form language or edit code |
| Repo and test harness | compile, run tests, train/eval models, generate artifacts | decide whether results are valid |
| Tracker/orchestrator | store run metadata, logs, artifacts, execution graphs | determine accept/reject semantics |

That split gives the CLI a very specific job: **be the narrow waist between flexible agent behavior and durable experimental truth**. In other words, the CLI should be responsible for any action that changes authoritative MLSpec state, and the agent should be responsible for the messy work of getting there. That recommendation is highly consistent with official tracker/orchestrator docs, which already treat telemetry and execution as separate concerns from interpretation. ţłÇciteţłéturn0search2ţłéturn22search0ţłéturn0search19ţłéturn13search0ţłü

The CLI should therefore own at least six categories of responsibility:

| CLI responsibility | Why it belongs in the CLI |
|---|---|
| State transitions | transitions must be typed and auditable |
| Immutable snapshots | protocol, commit, config, and dataset bindings must not be free-form |
| Evidence grading | this is policy, not narrative |
| Decision gating | accept/reject requires invariant checks |
| Audit and queries | consistency checks need deterministic execution |
| Integration adapters | external run data must be normalized before it becomes evidence |

By contrast, the agent should own five categories of responsibility:

| Agent responsibility | Why it belongs in the agent |
|---|---|
| Planning and decomposition | high-level reasoning is the agentÔÇÖs comparative advantage |
| Code modification | editing and iterating are flexible, local tasks |
| Cheap validation | unit tests, lint, smoke checks, shape checks are part of active iteration |
| Skill orchestration | one human request often spans many small operations |
| Explanation | humans need conversational summaries, options, and tradeoffs |

The agent should **not** be treated as trustworthy long-term memory. PROV-AGENTÔÇÖs core motivation is precisely that prompts, responses, and downstream actions need traceability because agent choices can propagate errors through a workflow. MLSpec should internalize that premise and assume the agent can forget, drift, shortcut, or rationalize. ţłÇciteţłéturn2search0ţłü

## Commands, skills, CLI primitives, and prompts

The system will stay confusing unless these four layers are separated cleanly:

| Layer | What it is | Example |
|---|---|---|
| Human request | natural-language intent from the human | ÔÇťTry label smoothing and tell me if itÔÇÖs worth a full run.ÔÇŁ |
| Agent skill | reusable multi-step procedure with preconditions and outputs | `skill.try_candidate_change` |
| CLI primitive | deterministic state mutation/query | `mlspec run begin`, `mlspec evidence classify` |
| Tool invocation | raw shell/script/tracker actions | `pytest`, `python train.py`, tracker API call |

That separation is the UX missing piece. A human should ask for **outcomes**, not for CLI verbs. The agent should translate those outcomes into a bounded skill. The skill should invoke CLI primitives to commit authoritative state changes. This separation also matches Design Science ResearchÔÇÖs view that artifacts should encode method, not just data. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search14ţłü

A strong skill catalog for v0 would look like this:

| Skill | Purpose | Typical steps | Outputs |
|---|---|---|---|
| `frame_case` | define or refine the question | inspect repo, ask for target metric/budget, draft case and protocol | case + protocol draft |
| `import_project` | bring a brownfield repo under MLSpec | detect tracker, parse configs, infer datasets/splits, mark unknowns | imported case + lineage gaps |
| `patch_code` | implement a candidate change | edit code, add/update tests, run local checks | patch + validation notes |
| `run_sanity` | verify basic correctness cheaply | run lint/tests/smoke, shape checks, tiny train/eval | low-grade evidence or bug report |
| `run_candidate` | execute a structured experiment | ensure clean snapshot, lock protocol, launch run, collect resources | run record |
| `compare_to_baseline` | produce comparison-ready evidence | locate matched baseline, compare splits/metrics/resources | evidence draft |
| `decide_case` | turn evidence into bounded conclusion | run audits, classify evidence, draft claim/decision | decision or rerun recommendation |
| `handoff_state` | preserve context across sessions/agents | summarize current case, pending risks, next best actions | structured handoff |

Each skill should have explicit preconditions and refusal conditions. For example, `decide_case` should refuse if there is no matched baseline, missing evaluator digest, unresolved material deviation, or insufficient run count. That refusal-oriented design is directly aligned with the purpose of provenance and audit: keep absent information absent instead of allowing the agent to fill it with narrative confidence. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search7ţłéturn2search0ţłü

The CLI itself should stay narrow and boring. A good v0 command set is below.

| CLI primitive | Responsibility |
|---|---|
| `mlspec case create` | create case root |
| `mlspec protocol draft` | write or update protocol draft |
| `mlspec protocol lock` | freeze protocol version for evidence-bearing runs |
| `mlspec workspace snapshot` | record commit, dirty state, config digests, env digest |
| `mlspec run begin` | create run record bound to protocol + snapshot |
| `mlspec run end` | finalize run outcome + actual resources + outputs |
| `mlspec evidence classify` | convert runs and metrics into evidence grade |
| `mlspec claim draft` | write explicit scoped claim |
| `mlspec decision issue` | accept, reject, inconclusive, rerun, archive |
| `mlspec audit` | run invariant checks |
| `mlspec import` | ingest from trackers, logs, files, or existing repos |
| `mlspec status` | summarize cases, risks, next actions |

The CLI should **not** expose ÔÇťfree-form write anythingÔÇŁ commands. If the CLI accepts unconstrained blobs for evidence or decisions, the whole system collapses back into markdown slop. The provenance and scientific-workflow sources both point toward typed, queryable lineage rather than purely narrative records. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search7ţłü

The agent prompts that matter most are not prose-heavy system prompts; they are short skill contracts. A good skill contract template is:

```text
SKILL CONTRACT
Goal:
Inputs:
Preconditions:
Default next steps:
Required CLI mutations:
Required local validations:
Maximum allowed claim:
Refuse if:
Outputs:
```

That form is especially effective because it maps well to PROV-AGENTÔÇÖs proposed modeling of prompts, model invocations, responses, and decisions as traceable workflow elements. ţłÇciteţłéturn2search0ţłü

## User stories and workflow shapes

The central UX answer is that the human usually works with **the agent as lab partner** and only rarely with the CLI directly. The human says what they want to learn or change. The agent proposes the next bounded move, executes it, and updates MLSpec through the CLI. The human only needs to intervene at ambiguity boundaries, priority changes, or decision boundaries. That is the most natural adaptation of adaptive case management to agentic engineering work. ţłÇciteţłéturn0search5ţłéturn2search0ţłü

### Greenfield with nothing set up

The greenfield user story should feel like this:

1. The human says: *ÔÇťI want to know whether loss reweighting helps on dataset D under a 12 GPU-hour cap.ÔÇŁ*
2. The agent inspects the repo or scaffolds one, identifies missing pieces, drafts a protocol, and proposes a baseline and metric.
3. The agent creates an MLSpec case, drafts the protocol, and asks only the irreducible clarifying questions: target metric, compute cap, and success criterion.
4. The agent writes or patches code, adds basic tests, runs smoke checks, and records low-grade evidence.
5. Only when the code is stable enough does the agent lock the protocol, snapshot the workspace, and launch structured runs.
6. The agent classifies evidence, compares against baseline, and either recommends a full run, a rerun, or a scoped decision.

This flow is consistent with the source pattern that exploratory work should accumulate history, while robust conclusions require exact protocol, compute, and reporting context. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search1ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłü

### Existing MLSpec project

The existing-project user story should be lighter:

1. The human says: *ÔÇťTry label smoothing as a cheap ablation.ÔÇŁ*
2. The agent reads the live case, protocol, open hypotheses, prior runs, and resource budget.
3. The agent decides whether this is scratch, structured, or decision mode.
4. The agent patches code, runs existing tests, and either stays in exploratory mode or promotes the idea to a real candidate run.
5. The agent updates the case and returns a concise summary: what changed, what evidence exists, what is still unknown, and the next cheapest informative step.

This is where MLSpec should feel most efficient, because case/history/protocol already exist. The existence of a case file and queryable lineage is exactly what CMMN and scientific-workflow systems are meant to make easier. ţłÇciteţłéturn0search5ţłéturn1search7ţłü

### Brownfield project with no MLSpec

Brownfield is the most delicate story, because missing provenance should stay missing.

1. The human says: *ÔÇťBring this repo under MLSpec and tell me what we can trust from prior results.ÔÇŁ*
2. The agent imports existing runs, logs, configs, tracker records, and artifacts.
3. The agent tries to infer datasets, splits, metric evaluators, and baselines, but every inference gets a confidence label.
4. Anything unverifiable becomes an explicit gap, not a filled-in guess.
5. The agent creates imported evidence that is capped in grade by missing lineage.
6. The agent recommends the minimal rerun set needed to upgrade legacy conclusions into protocol-grade evidence.

That behavior is especially important because provenance systems are strongest when they preserve lineage explicitly, and weakest when they silently invent it after the fact. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search7ţłü

A practical summary of the three stories is below.

| Scenario | Default interaction style | Biggest risk | MLSpec response |
|---|---|---|---|
| Greenfield | scaffold and guide | overdesign or missing baseline | start light, add protocol and baseline early |
| Existing MLSpec | continue case work | stale assumptions or unnoticed drift | read state first, then act |
| Brownfield | import and quarantine | fake lineage reconstruction | mark unknowns, cap evidence, propose reruns |

The question ÔÇťCan the human jump around fast?ÔÇŁ is therefore very relevant. The answer is **yes, but only in the modes where the system makes clear that the resulting evidence is exploratory**. MLSpec should never punish speed; it should punish unsupported certainty. That is the core UX principle. It also aligns well with VisTrailsÔÇÖ emphasis on preserving exploratory history rather than forcing premature formalization. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search1ţłü

## Code changes, correctness, and safety gates

This is the part that has to account most directly for agent weaknesses.

ML work almost always involves code changes: new model paths, new data transforms, new evaluation hooks, new baselines, bug fixes, instrumentation, or config changes. MLSpec should therefore treat **code modification as a first-class phase**, not as something outside the experiment process. The mistake would be to treat ÔÇťimplementationÔÇŁ and ÔÇťexperimentÔÇŁ as separate worlds. In practice, they interleave, but they should not be allowed to contaminate each other silently. The right model is: **code changes are fluid until a run is meant to count as evidence; then the workspace must be frozen and fingerprinted**. This is a design synthesis grounded in provenance, tracker metadata, and reproducibility reporting. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn6search2ţłü

A robust implementation ladder is:

| Phase | Purpose | Agent freedom | Required checks |
|---|---|---|---|
| Patch | modify code to realize idea | high | none beyond local sanity |
| Validate | confirm implementation is not obviously broken | medium | tests, lint, shape/data checks |
| Smoke | catch pipeline bugs cheaply | medium | tiny run, logs, metric presence |
| Candidate | test protocol-compatible version | lower | clean snapshot, fixed config, bound resources |
| Decision | support accept/reject judgment | lowest | full audit, matched baseline, evidence-grade gate |

That ladder is the simplest way to prevent ÔÇťsomething later got messed up and poisoned the result.ÔÇŁ Every evidence-bearing run should be tied to a **workspace snapshot** that includes commit hash, dirty-tree status, tracked diff digest if dirty execution is allowed, config digests, environment digest, and dataset/split digests. After a run completes, subsequent code changes should never retroactively alter the meaning of that run; if the agent edits code again, that creates a new candidate state and any future evidence must cite the new snapshot. That rule is straight from the logic of provenance and tracker lineage. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn13search0ţłü

The safety gates before a decision-grade run should be explicit:

| Gate | What it blocks |
|---|---|
| clean or explicitly snapshotted workspace | hidden code drift |
| locked protocol version | moving-target evaluation |
| explicit baseline reference | ungrounded comparison |
| evaluator digest attached | silent metric changes |
| split manifest attached | leakage or noncomparable splits |
| required tests passed | obvious implementation breakage |
| resource budget declared | underpowered final claims |
| previous deviations resolved or acknowledged | silent protocol drift |

These gates are where MLSpec should be deliberately rigid. Everything before them can remain much more fluid. That division preserves speed without surrendering rigor. ţłÇciteţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłü

The agent-specific controls should be intentionally adversarial, because the user is right: agents can be lazy, fake completion, and lose track of long arcs. PROV-AGENT is relevant here because it treats prompts, responses, and decisions as provenance-bearing workflow elements rather than invisible internal cognition. MLSpec should build on that by requiring the following for high-stakes actions: captured command, captured stdout/stderr, explicit refusal to infer missing facts, periodic state summaries, and automatic comparison of the live workspace against the cited evidence snapshot. ţłÇciteţłéturn2search0ţłü

A strong set of agent-failure countermeasures is:

| Agent weakness | Countermeasure |
|---|---|
| forgets long-term context | structured `handoff_state` artifact after each major skill |
| claims success from intention | no evidence from planned runs; only observed run ids may be cited |
| hides failure output | stdout/stderr artifacts mandatory for failed and decision-grade runs |
| gets lazy with testing | skill contracts require minimum local validation before evidence runs |
| edits too much at once | worktree- or patch-scoped changes per candidate run |
| overstates results | decision gate maps evidence grade to allowed conclusion form |
| silently changes metric/eval | evaluator and split digests are compared automatically |

The result should not be ÔÇťtrust the agent less by making it slow.ÔÇŁ It should be ÔÇťassume the agent is unreliable where provenance matters, and give it freedom elsewhere.ÔÇŁ That is the right UX compromise.

```mermaid
stateDiagram-v2
  [*] --> Scratch
  Scratch --> Scratch: patch / test / tiny runs
  Scratch --> Structured: promote_candidate
  Structured --> Scratch: major redesign
  Structured --> Decision: full protocol satisfied
  Structured --> Structured: rerun / compare / refine
  Decision --> Structured: audit fails or new change introduced
  Decision --> Resolved: accept / reject / inconclusive
```

## Audit, evaluation, and the first usable prototype

The best UX is useless if the audit layer is weak. The audit surface should answer the questions the human actually cares about:

- **What changed?**
- **What evidence do we have?**
- **What are we allowed to conclude?**
- **What is the cheapest next informative step?**

That last question is especially important. A good agent should not just report invalidity; it should recommend the next minimal action that would upgrade the evidence. That kind of next-step guidance is a design recommendation, but it follows from the resource-aware evidence framing and the practical reality emphasized in reproducibility work that compute is limited and should be allocated deliberately. ţłÇciteţłéturn6search2ţłü

The most useful UX-facing audit queries are:

| Audit query | Why the human cares |
|---|---|
| ÔÇťWhy canÔÇÖt I accept this result?ÔÇŁ | makes the decision gate legible |
| ÔÇťWhat changed since the last evidence-bearing run?ÔÇŁ | catches contamination from newer edits |
| ÔÇťWhat is missing for decision-grade evidence?ÔÇŁ | tells the agent what to do next |
| ÔÇťAre my compared runs actually comparable?ÔÇŁ | blocks misleading wins |
| ÔÇťWhat prior conclusions are now stale?ÔÇŁ | handles brownfield drift and ongoing code evolution |
| ÔÇťWhat is the cheapest next run that improves certainty?ÔÇŁ | aligns rigor with constrained compute |

This is also where the adversarial fixture set should shift from purely data/provenance failures to **UX failures**.

| Fixture | What it tests |
|---|---|
| agent says ÔÇťdoneÔÇŁ after only code edits | separation between implementation and evidence |
| agent cites a planned or failed run as support | evidence source validation |
| agent compares against wrong split | comparison audit usability |
| agent launches expensive run without baseline | budget-aware planning |
| agent keeps editing code after a supposedly final run | snapshot contamination detection |
| brownfield import silently backfills unknown dataset version | refusal to hallucinate lineage |
| human asks for a quick answer and agent overclaims from proxy run | fluidity without fake certainty |
| existing MLSpec case has stale protocol but agent fails to notice | read-state-before-act discipline |

The first usable prototype should therefore be more UX-complete than feature-complete. A strong minimal stack is:

| Component | Recommended v0 choice |
|---|---|
| state store | SQLite or append-only JSONL with typed validation |
| CLI | thin typed control plane |
| agent layer | chat interface plus skill contracts |
| code execution | normal repo tooling and shell |
| tracker integration | first-class adapter to ţłÇurlţłéMLflowţłéturn0search2ţłü |
| orchestrator integration | optional adapter to ţłÇurlţłéKubeflowţłéturn0search19ţłü |
| provenance export | PROV-like graph export for debug/inspection |
| report views | markdown or HTML projections from state, never canonical source |

That ordering matters. It is more important to get **skill contracts, workspace snapshots, evidence grading, and decision audits** right than to build many integrations early. The source base strongly supports that prioritization because provenance, reproducibility, and design-science rigor are where the hardest failures live, while execution tooling can be integrated incrementally. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search14ţłéturn6search2ţłü

## Recommended design decisions

The design conclusions that seem highest-confidence from the source base and from the UX problem you raised are these:

| Decision | Recommendation |
|---|---|
| Main user experience | chat with the agent, not direct CLI operation |
| Trust boundary | CLI owns truth; agent owns effort |
| Workflow style | tiered rigidity: fluid exploration, strict decision boundaries |
| Unit of work | case-centric, not task-list-centric |
| Code changes | first-class and expected, but frozen per evidence-bearing run |
| Agent control | skills with preconditions, outputs, and refusal rules |
| Brownfield support | import with explicit unknowns and evidence caps |
| Default behavior under uncertainty | `INSUFFICIENT_EVIDENCE`, not narrative guessing |

The single best implementation heuristic is:

> **Do not try to make the whole workflow rigid. Make only the epistemically dangerous transitions rigid.**

That gives you the UX you were asking for. It preserves the speed and improvisational value of agents during exploration, but prevents the exact failure mode MLSpec exists to stop: turning messy, partial, underpowered work into strong, durable ML conclusions. That is the point where the provenance work, case-management framing, reproducibility guidance, and agent-trace literature all line up. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn2search0ţłü

## Open questions and limitations

Some important implementation questions remain open because the infrastructure assumptions are unspecified. The best examples are multi-agent coordination, remote execution trust boundaries, data privacy and secret handling, the choice between strict clean-tree enforcement and dirty-workspace snapshotting, and statistical policies for ÔÇťdecision-gradeÔÇŁ claims across different ML domains. The primary sources reviewed here strongly constrain the provenance, case, telemetry, and audit design, but they do not uniquely determine those policy choices. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn1search14ţłü

The safest next step is therefore not more ontology work. It is a UX prototype that proves four things end to end: the human can mostly stay in chat, the agent can move fast in scratch mode, the CLI can block unsupported upgrades into stronger evidence/decisions, and the system can explain clearly **why** a conclusion is or is not allowed. If those four things work, the rest of MLSpec becomes much easier to iterate. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search14ţłéturn2search0ţłü</UX><implementation># MLSpec Implementation Theory

## Executive summary

The implementation that best fits the underlying theory is a **chat-first, agent-mediated, CLI-enforced control plane**. The human should usually talk to an agent, not to the CLI. The agent should plan, edit code, run checks, and propose actions through reusable skills. The CLI should be the narrow waist that owns authoritative state transitions, provenance capture, evidence classification, and decision gating. That division matches the core lessons from PROVÔÇÖs separation of agents, activities, and entities; CMMNÔÇÖs case-centric handling of messy, non-linear work; MLflowÔÇÖs run/artifact telemetry model; KubeflowÔÇÖs orchestration and metadata model; VisTrailsÔÇÖ emphasis on preserving exploratory history; PROV-AGENTÔÇÖs insistence that prompts, responses, and decisions be traceable; and Design Science ResearchÔÇÖs focus on building artifacts that solve a real problem and can be evaluated against failure cases. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn22search0ţłéturn0search19ţłéturn13search0ţłéturn1search1ţłéturn2search0ţłéturn1search14ţłü

The main implementation consequence is that **fluidity belongs in exploration, and rigidity belongs at epistemically dangerous boundaries**. Code edits, fast tests, and cheap exploratory runs should be easy. But the system should become strict when a run is meant to count as evidence or when a conclusion is meant to become durable: protocol frozen, workspace snapshotted, resources recorded, deviations declared, comparators validated, evidence graded, and decisions audited. That approach is strongly aligned with the scientific-workflow and reproducibility literature, which values exploratory iteration but also requires exact tracking of runs, infrastructure, metrics, and variation before conclusions can be trusted. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search7ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłü

The best MVP is therefore not a giant platform. It is a small set of typed nouns, a thin CLI with JSON-first machine interfaces and readable human views, a set of agent-facing skills with explicit stop conditions and refusal rules, a SQLite-first state store with a JSONL debug adapter, and an adversarial fixture suite that proves the system prevents overclaiming. Everything else, including tracker integration, orchestration, and dashboards, should be secondary. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search14ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn0search19ţłéturn1search7ţłü

## Implementation architecture

The clean implementation stack is:

1. **Human intent layer** for goals, priorities, and approvals.
2. **Agent skill layer** for planning, code edits, execution, and explanation.
3. **MLSpec CLI control plane** for typed state mutations and invariant checks.
4. **State store** for cases, protocols, runs, evidence, and decisions.
5. **Execution backends** such as the local repo, test harnesses, MLflow, or Kubeflow.

That layering follows naturally from the source set: PROV gives the traceability grammar, CMMN gives the ÔÇťevolving caseÔÇŁ shell, MLflow and Kubeflow provide sources of execution metadata rather than epistemic truth, and PROV-AGENT extends provenance to agent actions and prompts. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn0search19ţłéturn13search0ţłéturn2search0ţłü

```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
    participant H as Human
    participant A as Agent
    participant S as Skill
    participant C as MLSpec CLI
    participant M as MLSpec Store
    participant R as Repo/Test Harness
    participant T as Tracker/Orchestrator

    H->>A: "Try label smoothing and tell me if it's worth it"
    A->>S: select skill(s)
    S->>C: status / case show / protocol show
    C->>M: read state
    M-->>C: current case state
    C-->>S: JSON result
    S->>R: patch code, run tests, run smoke or candidate job
    R->>T: optional metadata/artifacts
    S->>C: snapshot create / run begin / run end
    C->>M: persist authoritative records
    T-->>S: run ids, metrics, artifacts
    S->>C: evidence classify / audit / decision issue
    C->>M: validate, downgrade, or block
    C-->>S: result + warnings + blockers
    S-->>A: bounded summary
    A-->>H: what changed, what evidence exists, what is allowed next
```

The most important architectural choice is that the CLI is **not just a convenience wrapper**. It is the trusted boundary. The agent may use shell tools, edit code, run tests, and even talk to trackers directly, but nothing becomes authoritative MLSpec truth unless it passes through the CLI. That recommendation is a design synthesis, but it is exactly how you preserve the provenance and lifecycle discipline implied by PROV, CMMN, scientific workflows, and agent provenance while still keeping the execution layer flexible. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search5ţłéturn1search7ţłéturn2search0ţłü

## Control flow and skill mechanics

The table below answers the control-flow and skill-mechanics questions directly. These are implementation recommendations derived from the source constraints above; they are not themselves standardized APIs. The strongest source pressure here comes from CMMNÔÇÖs case-lifecycle thinking, PROV-AGENTÔÇÖs traceability requirement for agent actions, and DSRÔÇÖs emphasis on making the artifact evaluable rather than magical. ţłÇciteţłéturn0search5ţłéturn2search0ţłéturn1search14ţłü

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q1** How does the agent invoke CLI commands? | Yes: one-shot subprocess execution such as `spawn("mlspec", [..., "--json"])` is the right default. If the host runtime has a richer tool API, wrap subprocesses there, but preserve the same semantics. |
| **Q2** What does the CLI output? | Human-readable text by default; structured JSON with `--json`; ANSI color only when writing to a TTY. Agents should always use `--json`. |
| **Q3** How does the agent chain commands? | By parsing IDs and fields from JSON responses. Do not scrape human text. Do not rely on temporary files except for explicit artifact paths or `@file` inputs. |
| **Q4** What goes in `Default next steps` in a skill contract? | A bounded **decision tree**, not vague prose: ordered steps, branch conditions, stop conditions, and escalation rules. |
| **Q5** When does the agent stop looping and report? | Stop on the first of: requested action complete, meaningful blocker encountered, human approval required, budget exhausted, evidence target reached, or decision blocked with a clear next action. |
| **Q6** What if a CLI command fails mid-skill? | The skill should classify the failure: `transient`, `user_fix_needed`, `invariant_block`, or `internal_bug`. Recover only from transient or read-only-query failures. Abort on invariant or state-integrity failures. |
| **Q7** Can skills call other skills? | Yes, but only through a parent orchestration skill. Prefer a shallow tree: one planner skill coordinating several leaf skills. |
| **Q8** Is a skill just a prompt template? | No. A skill should be **prompt + imperative contract**: inputs, preconditions, steps, required CLI mutations, validations, maximum allowed claim, refusal rules, outputs. |
| **Q9** How does the agent decide which skill to load? | From intent classification, current case state, and current mode. Use explicit routing heuristics rather than free-form whim. |
| **Q10** What if no skill matches? | Fall back to a `triage` or `frame_case` skill, not unconstrained free-form action. The fallback skill should narrow the task, ask minimal clarifying questions, and create bounded next steps. |

A strong skill contract is short and machine-legible. It should encode what the agent is allowed to do, what facts must be recorded, and what the strongest allowed claim is. That design directly addresses the agent-failure patterns that PROV-AGENT is concerned with: invisible prompts, undocumented decisions, and weak accountability for downstream effects. ţłÇciteţłéturn2search0ţłü

```text
SKILL CONTRACT
Name: run_candidate
Goal: Execute a protocol-compatible ML experiment and return classified evidence
Inputs:
  - case_id
  - protocol_id
  - candidate_change_description
Preconditions:
  - protocol is locked
  - workspace can be snapshotted
  - baseline reference exists for comparative claims
Default next steps:
  1. read case/protocol/status
  2. patch code if needed
  3. run local validations
  4. create snapshot
  5. begin run
  6. execute job
  7. end run with actual resources
  8. classify evidence
  9. run audit
Stop conditions:
  - validation fails
  - human approval required
  - evidence reaches target grade
  - decision is blocked with clear reason
Maximum allowed claim:
  - no stronger than returned evidence grade
Refuse if:
  - no protocol
  - no snapshot
  - comparator is undefined for a comparative claim
Outputs:
  - run_id
  - evidence_id
  - audit_report
  - bounded summary
```

The agent should also route work through **modes**: `scratch`, `structured`, and `decision`. Those modes are not just UI labels; they shape what the agent is allowed to promise. Scratch mode may patch code and run cheap experiments, but it cannot output anything stronger than ÔÇťdebugging signalÔÇŁ or ÔÇťworth promoting.ÔÇŁ Structured mode can create partial or decision-grade evidence. Decision mode can only operate when the prerequisites for issuing a decision are already close to satisfied. This mode split is a direct implementation of the ÔÇťfluid exploration, rigid conclusionÔÇŁ principle. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search1ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn1search14ţłü

## Minimal schema and state

The MVP noun set should be **slightly larger than the absolute minimum**, because the theory breaks if protocol, claims, or run snapshots are collapsed away. The right minimum is:

- `Case`
- `Protocol`
- `Snapshot`
- `Run`
- `Deviation`
- `Evidence`
- `Claim`
- `Decision`

That set is the smallest one that still preserves the critical distinctions between intent, contract, execution, support, and conclusion. PROV strongly supports preserving the difference between entities, activities, agents, and plans; MLflow and Kubeflow strongly support treating runs and artifacts as explicit records rather than incidental byproducts; and reproducibility guidance strongly supports separating procedure, evaluation, and reporting. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn13search0ţłéturn6search2ţłü

The table below answers the schema questions directly.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q11** Minimum noun set for MVP? | `Case + Protocol + Snapshot + Run + Evidence + Claim + Decision + Deviation`. `Protocol` is required for any evidence-bearing or decision-bearing work, but optional for pure scratch exploration. |
| **Q12** Can you have a Decision without a Claim? | No. Every `Decision` must cite exactly one `Claim`, though a case can contain many claims. |
| **Q13** What is a Claim? | A structured object with at least `statement`, `scope`, `comparator`, and `target_metric`. Free text alone is too weak. |
| **Q14** Is Artifact required in MVP? | A full first-class `Artifact` table can be deferred if `Snapshot` and `Run.output_refs` exist. But artifact digests and URIs must still be recordable. |
| **Q15** Is MetricResult required? | It can be nested inside `Evidence` in MVP as a typed list; a separate first-class noun becomes useful once querying gets richer. |
| **Q16** Exact shape of ResourceBudget? | MVP minimum: `gpu_hours`, `wallclock_hours`, `data_fraction`, `seeds`, `epochs`; plus optional `accelerator_type`, `peak_vram_gb`, and `num_devices`. |
| **Q17** Is Actor required? | In MVP, a minimal `actor_ref` string on every mutation is enough, with reserved identities such as `human:<id>` and `agent:<id>`. A full `Actor` table can come later. |

A practical MVP shape is below. This is a product design recommendation informed by the source set; it is not copied from any one standard. The closest conceptual scaffolding is PROVÔÇÖs entity/activity/agent/plan model plus run-centric metadata patterns from MLflow and Kubeflow. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn0search19ţłü

```ts
type Id = string; // UUIDv7
type ResourceBudget = {
  gpu_hours: number;
  wallclock_hours: number;
  data_fraction: number; // 0..1
  seeds: number;
  epochs: number;
  accelerator_type?: string;
  peak_vram_gb?: number;
  num_devices?: number;
};

type Case = {
  id: Id;
  question: string;
  mode: "scratch" | "structured" | "decision";
  status: "open" | "ready" | "running" | "observed" | "resolved" | "archived";
  current_protocol_id?: Id;
  actor_ref: string;
  created_at: string;
};

type Protocol = {
  id: Id;
  case_id: Id;
  version: number;
  objective: string;
  baseline_selector?: string;
  metric_spec: { name: string; direction: "max" | "min"; split: string };
  required_resources: ResourceBudget;
  min_decision_grade: "decision_grade" | "replicated";
  locked_at?: string;
};

type Snapshot = {
  id: Id;
  case_id: Id;
  commit_hash?: string;
  dirty_tree: boolean;
  diff_digest?: string;
  config_digests: string[];
  dataset_digests: string[];
  split_manifest_digest?: string;
  evaluator_digest?: string;
  environment_digest?: string;
  actor_ref: string;
  created_at: string;
};

type Run = {
  id: Id;
  case_id: Id;
  protocol_id?: Id;
  snapshot_id?: Id;
  kind: "smoke" | "proxy" | "full" | "replication";
  status: "planned" | "running" | "completed" | "failed" | "aborted";
  command: string[];
  tracker_refs: string[];
  actual_resources?: ResourceBudget;
  output_refs: string[];
  started_at?: string;
  ended_at?: string;
};

type Deviation = {
  id: Id;
  run_id: Id;
  category: string;
  severity: "minor" | "material" | "fatal";
  impact: "none" | "weakens" | "invalidates";
  note: string;
};

type Evidence = {
  id: Id;
  case_id: Id;
  run_ids: Id[];
  metrics: Array<{
    name: string;
    split: string;
    value: number;
    dispersion?: number;
    seed?: number;
  }>;
  grade: "smoke" | "proxy" | "partial" | "decision_grade" | "replicated" | "invalid";
  protocol_satisfied: "yes" | "partial" | "no";
  baseline_run_ids?: Id[];
  deviation_ids: Id[];
  summary: string;
};

type Claim = {
  id: Id;
  case_id: Id;
  statement: string;
  scope: string;
  comparator?: string;
  target_metric?: string;
};

type Decision = {
  id: Id;
  case_id: Id;
  claim_id: Id;
  status: "accept" | "reject" | "inconclusive" | "rerun" | "archive";
  evidence_ids: Id[];
  rationale: string;
  actor_ref: string;
  created_at: string;
};
```

The repository or store interface should also be explicit. You asked to see it, and it should be small. PROV and scientific-workflow systems both favor queryable provenance stores; MLflow and Kubeflow likewise center queryable runs and metadata. That implies a thin state repository with typed writes and filtered reads. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search7ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn13search0ţłü

```ts
interface MLSpecStore {
  createCase(input: CreateCaseInput): Case;
  getCase(id: Id): Case | null;
  listCases(filter?: CaseFilter): Case[];

  draftProtocol(input: DraftProtocolInput): Protocol;
  lockProtocol(caseId: Id, protocolId: Id): Protocol;

  createSnapshot(input: CreateSnapshotInput): Snapshot;

  beginRun(input: BeginRunInput): Run;
  endRun(runId: Id, input: EndRunInput): Run;

  recordDeviation(input: RecordDeviationInput): Deviation;
  classifyEvidence(input: ClassifyEvidenceInput): Evidence;

  createClaim(input: CreateClaimInput): Claim;
  issueDecision(input: IssueDecisionInput): Decision;

  audit(scope: AuditScope): AuditReport;
  status(scope: StatusScope): StatusReport;
}
```

## Evidence, decisions, and audit

The evidence and decision layer is where the theory becomes implementation. The right model is that the **agent may propose**, but the **CLI computes and enforces**. Specifically, the agent may nominate a baseline, suggest a claim, or request a target evidence grade, but the CLI should compute the actual evidence grade from observed resources, comparability rules, deviations, and protocol thresholds. That recommendation is consistent with the reproducibility literatureÔÇÖs insistence on exact reporting of run conditions and with the central source distinction between telemetry and validity. ţłÇciteţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn1search7ţłü

The table below answers the evidence and decision questions directly.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q18** How is evidence grade computed? | The agent submits candidate inputs; the CLI computes the grade deterministically from protocol thresholds, actual resources, comparability checks, and deviations. |
| **Q19** Who decides the matched baseline? | The agent or human proposes it; the CLI validates comparability. |
| **Q20** Exact criteria for `decision_grade`? | Yes: `resource_completeness >= 1.0`, `run.status = completed`, `protocol locked`, `matched baseline` for comparative claims, `split manifest match`, `evaluator digest match`, `no fatal deviations`, `no unresolved material deviations`, `snapshot complete`, and `seed_count >= protocol minimum`; dispersion is required whenever multiple seeds are required or present. |
| **Q21** What if the agent claims `decision_grade` at 30% resources? | The CLI should **downgrade** the grade to the maximum allowed grade and return warnings. In strict mode, it may also fail the command. |
| **Q22** How is variance handled? | Required for `decision_grade` whenever protocol demands multiple seeds or multiple runs. If only one seed is required by protocol, dispersion is optional but the limitation must be explicit. |
| **Q23** What does `inconclusive` mean? | Evidence exists, but it is either too weak, too conflicting, too non-comparable, or too narrow in scope to support `accept` or `reject`. |
| **Q24** Can you issue `reject` on negative `decision_grade` evidence? | Yes. `decision_grade` measures evidentiary strength, not positivity. Strong negative evidence supports a strong rejection. |
| **Q25** What does a blocked decision return? | A structured failure object: machine code, blocking invariants, current evidence cap, and suggested next actions. |

A good default evidence rubric is below. These thresholds are recommended defaults, not standardized universal laws. They are justified because the reproducibility checklist and scientific-workflow sources repeatedly emphasize run counts, compute, split/metric comparability, and variation reporting as prerequisites for credible conclusions. ţłÇciteţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłéturn1search7ţłü

| Grade | Default interpretation | Typical allowed output |
|---|---|---|
| `smoke` | sanity check, tiny resource fraction, wiring/debug focus | ÔÇťThe pipeline runs / fails in this specific way.ÔÇŁ |
| `proxy` | reduced-budget or reduced-scope signal | ÔÇťThis looks promising enough to promote.ÔÇŁ |
| `partial` | meaningful but incomplete support; missing some requirement | ÔÇťPreliminary signal under stated limits.ÔÇŁ |
| `decision_grade` | all required conditions for the protocol scope satisfied | ÔÇťAccept or reject for scope S under protocol P.ÔÇŁ |
| `replicated` | `decision_grade` plus explicit replication requirement satisfied | ÔÇťStronger accept/reject recommendation.ÔÇŁ |
| `invalid` | lineage hole, fatal deviation, or comparability failure | ÔÇťNo decision; rerun or repair required.ÔÇŁ |

The decision API should be equally strict. A good result object for a blocked decision is:

```json
{
  "ok": false,
  "command": "decision.issue",
  "code": "INSUFFICIENT_EVIDENCE",
  "message": "Claim cannot be resolved as accept/reject.",
  "data": {
    "claim_id": "clm_01...",
    "requested_status": "accept",
    "max_allowed_status": "inconclusive",
    "evidence_cap": "partial"
  },
  "blocking_invariants": [
    "BASELINE_NOT_COMPARABLE",
    "RESOURCE_UNDERRUN",
    "MISSING_DISPERSION"
  ],
  "suggested_next_actions": [
    "rerun with protocol-required seeds=5",
    "attach matched baseline on identical split+evaluator",
    "reclassify evidence after rerun"
  ]
}
```

The audit layer should enforce the adversarial cases you care about most: citing planned work as evidence, comparing non-comparable runs, cherry-picking the best run without a selection rule, promoting underpowered runs to decision-grade, issuing decisions without claims, and classifying evidence against a mutable or missing snapshot. Those checks are a direct operationalization of the provenance, reproducibility, and DSR literature: the artifact is only good if it prevents the failure modes it exists to stop. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn1search14ţłü

## Human workflow and user stories

The human workflow should be **agent-first and mode-aware**. The human usually gives intent, priorities, and approval thresholds. The agent reads the current case, chooses or asks for mode if ambiguous, executes one or more bounded skills, and returns a concise checkpoint only at meaningful boundaries. That recommendation follows from CMMNÔÇÖs adaptive work model and from PROV-AGENTÔÇÖs treatment of agent actions as part of the workflow rather than invisible internal cognition. ţłÇciteţłéturn0search5ţłéturn2search0ţłü

The table below answers the human/agent interaction questions.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q26** How does the agent know the mode? | Infer from utterance + current case status, but let the human override. Default to `scratch` if ambiguous, never `decision`. |
| **Q27** What does ÔÇťworth itÔÇŁ mean? | By default: ÔÇťworth promoting to a more expensive structured run,ÔÇŁ not ÔÇťfinal accept/reject.ÔÇŁ |
| **Q28** What does the agent say and when? | Not after every command. Report at phase boundaries: plan chosen, blocker found, expensive run requested, evidence classified, or decision/audit completed. |
| **Q29** Can the human interrupt mid-skill? | Yes. The skill should persist a partial handoff and either stop safely or leave long-running jobs detached but tracked. |
| **Q30** Can one request trigger multiple skills? | Yes. A planner skill may orchestrate multiple leaf skills for one human request. |
| **Q31** What does the human see while the agent works? | Concise streaming phase updates by default, with optional verbose command/log detail. |
| **Q32** How granular are human approvals? | Default: human approves expensive/destructive actions, protocol locks that imply real decision-bearing work, and any final published decision. Cheap local validation can be autonomous. |

Mode inference should be conservative. If a human says, ÔÇťtry label smoothing and tell me if itÔÇÖs worth it,ÔÇŁ the agent should interpret that as scratch or structured mode depending on the existing case, and the output should usually be ÔÇťworth promoting / not worth promoting / blocked by unknowns,ÔÇŁ not ÔÇťaccepted into the system.ÔÇŁ That keeps the workflow fluid without sacrificing rigor. The principle is exactly the same one visible in exploratory scientific workflows and reproducibility checklists: fast iteration is fine, but certainty must be earned. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search1ţłéturn6search2ţłü

A practical user story matrix is below.

| Scenario | What the human says | What the agent does | What the human gets back |
|---|---|---|---|
| Greenfield | ÔÇťI want to know if X helps under a 12 GPU-hour budget.ÔÇŁ | frames case, drafts protocol, patches code if needed, runs validations, promotes candidate runs | case summary, proposed protocol, initial evidence, next cheapest step |
| Existing MLSpec project | ÔÇťTry label smoothing and tell me if itÔÇÖs worth it.ÔÇŁ | reads case/protocol/history, patches code, runs scratch or structured experiment, classifies evidence | bounded recommendation tied to current case |
| Brownfield without MLSpec | ÔÇťBring this repo under MLSpec and tell me what we can trust.ÔÇŁ | scans repo, tracker, configs, logs; imports what is knowable; marks unknowns; caps legacy evidence; proposes reruns | imported case, confidence gaps, trustable vs untrustable prior results |

The code-change story should be explicit. Nearly all meaningful ML work involves code changes, and MLSpec should treat that as normal. The right ladder is: **patch Ôćĺ validate Ôćĺ smoke Ôćĺ candidate Ôćĺ decision**. The agent can move fluidly through patch and validate, but once the agent wants a run to count as evidence, it must create a snapshot and bind the run to that snapshot. If the code changes again after the run, the past run is not contaminated so long as the runÔÇÖs snapshot is intact; if no snapshot exists, the evidence should be invalid or capped severely. That is exactly how provenance should protect you from agent drift. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn6search2ţłü

The MNIST example becomes much clearer under this model.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q61** How does the agent know which repo in the MNIST example? | Default to the current working directory or explicitly attached workspace. If ambiguous, ask once. |
| **Q62** What can the agent do now that it could not do before? | Not just run the experiment, but bind it to a case, snapshot the code/config/data context, grade the evidence, and produce a bounded claim. |
| **Q63** Roughly how many CLI commands for an end-to-end MNIST story? | Usually 8ÔÇô14 authoritative CLI calls, plus many non-authoritative shell/test operations. |
| **Q64** What does the human see when it is done? | A compact summary with: what changed, which run(s) matter, evidence grade, blocked or allowed conclusions, and next actions. |

## CLI, storage, import, and host integration

The CLI should be small, typed, and JSON-first for agents. The core surface should remain close to the theory and avoid free-form mutation endpoints. This is consistent with the strong source pattern that provenance and scientific workflows are most valuable when the lineage is queryable and typed, and that trackers/orchestrators should feed data into a normalized metadata layer rather than becoming the validity layer themselves. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search7ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn13search0ţłü

The exact core command surface I recommend is eight **stateful command groups**:

| Group | Primary verbs | Purpose |
|---|---|---|
| `case` | `create`, `show`, `list`, `archive` | case root and status |
| `protocol` | `draft`, `show`, `lock` | experimental contract |
| `snapshot` | `create`, `show` | freeze code/config/data/env context |
| `run` | `begin`, `end`, `show`, `list` | execution record |
| `evidence` | `classify`, `show` | convert runs into bounded support |
| `claim` | `create`, `show` | explicit scoped assertion |
| `decision` | `issue`, `show` | allowed conclusion |
| `audit` | `run`, `show` | invariant enforcement |

Two additional **non-core views/adapters** are worth having from the start, but they are not part of the minimal stateful surface:

- `status` for a synthesized human/agent overview
- `import` for brownfield, MLflow, or Kubeflow ingestion

That ordering solves your earlier tension about ÔÇťeight primitivesÔÇŁ versus practical usability: eight groups own authoritative state, while `status` and `import` are projections and ingesters.

The CLI contract should be stable and envelope-based. This answers the command-output questions directly.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q33** Exact command surface? | The eight groups above. `status` and `import` are auxiliary. |
| **Q34** Success output shape? | In `--json`, always return a single envelope with `ok`, `command`, `data`, `warnings`, `meta`. |
| **Q35** Failure output shape? | In `--json`, still return a single envelope, but with `ok: false`, `code`, `message`, `blocking_invariants`, and `suggested_next_actions`; exit non-zero. |
| **Q36** Does `audit` do pass/fail only? | No. It should return a full invariant report plus a summary severity. |
| **Q37** What does `status` show? | Human summary by default; machine-readable aggregate state with `--json`. |
| **Q38** Interactive mode? | Not in MVP. Keep it one-shot and scriptable. Add TUI or REPL later only if needed. |
| **Q39** `--resources` format? | JSON object or `@file.json`. Do not invent a custom DSL. |

A standard JSON envelope should look like this:

```json
{
  "ok": true,
  "command": "run.begin",
  "data": {
    "run_id": "run_01JV...",
    "case_id": "case_01JV...",
    "protocol_id": "prot_01JV..."
  },
  "warnings": [],
  "meta": {
    "schema_version": "0.1.0",
    "store_revision": 184
  }
}
```

The store should be **SQLite by default**. That gives you typed queries, transactions, indexes, and enough concurrency for small teams without premature infrastructure. A JSONL adapter is still valuable, but mainly for debugging, replication, and fixture authoring. The source base does not prescribe SQLite specifically, but it strongly points toward a queryable metadata store rather than markdown-only state. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search7ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn13search0ţłü

The storage questions are best answered as follows:

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q45** Is the repository interface defined? | It should be explicitly defined in code, as shown earlier under `MLSpecStore`. |
| **Q46** How does the agent query state? | Prefer typed `show`, `list`, `status`, and `audit` filters first. Add a generic `query` command later only if needed. |
| **Q47** How does the JSONL adapter work? | One append-only `events.jsonl` per case under `.mlspec/cases/<case_id>/events.jsonl`; loaders materialize current state from events. |
| **Q48** What happens to IDs? | Use store-generated UUIDv7 identifiers so writes are sortable and globally unique. |
| **Q49** How does the agent get the latest case ID? | From the JSON envelope returned by the command. Optional convenience: `.mlspec/session.json` may store current context, but agents should not rely solely on ambient state. |

A practical on-disk shape is:

```text
.mlspec/
  config.yaml
  state.sqlite                 # canonical store
  session.json                 # optional current context
  cases/
    case_01JV.../
      events.jsonl             # optional debug/event mirror
      projections/
        summary.md
        audit.json
```

Brownfield import should be strict about what is truly knowable. This directly follows from provenance and scientific-workflow practice: inferred lineage must not be confused with observed lineage. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search7ţłü

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q40** What can we infer automatically? | Often: tracker type, experiment/run names, metric names, config files, coarse dataset names, rough baseline candidates. Rarely: split equivalence, evaluator equivalence, exact dataset digests, or valid comparator identity without explicit artifacts. |
| **Q41** How does the agent know what to import? | Start by scanning the current repo and common tracker locations; ask the human only if multiple plausible roots or trackers exist. |
| **Q42** What does ÔÇťmark unknownsÔÇŁ mean? | Persist `null` or `unknown` values plus a `confidence`/`verification_required` marker. Do not silently backfill. |
| **Q43** What is the import UX? | Yes: the human can say ÔÇťbring this repo under MLSpec,ÔÇŁ and the agent should do the scan, infer what it can, mark gaps, and return a trust report. |
| **Q44** How does the agent know the tracker? | Detect via lockfiles, imports, env vars, config files, directories like `mlruns/`, Kubeflow manifests, or CI scripts. |

The host-runtime questions about OpenCode are necessarily more tentative because those specifics were not part of the reviewed standards and primary sources. The safest approach is to build MLSpec so that host-specific command or skill discovery is only a thin wrapper over the same internal contracts.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q56** How does a skill trigger a subagent in OpenCode? | If OpenCode supports subagent frontmatter such as `agent: "plan"`, use it as a host wrapper around the planner skill. Do not make MLSpec semantics depend on that specific mechanism. |
| **Q57** Can skills use tools beyond the CLI? | Yes. They should be allowed to use repo tools like `pytest`, training scripts, linters, and tracker APIs, but only the CLI should change authoritative MLSpec state. |
| **Q58** Difference between an OpenCode command and a skill? | A command is a user-visible entrypoint; a skill is a reusable capability the agent can call internally. `/mlspec` is a power-user/manual entrypoint, not the primary UX. |
| **Q59** How does a skill get discovered? | If OpenCode auto-indexes `.opencode/skills/*/SKILL.md`, use that. If not, register skills explicitly. Treat discovery as host-runtime configuration, not MLSpec core logic. |
| **Q60** What permissions should the skill/agent have? | Use least-privilege profiles: local read/write repo access for patch skills, shell/test permissions for validation skills, explicit approval for destructive or expensive operations, and no raw secret storage in MLSpec state. |

## Adversarial cases, testing, and operations

The adversarial cases must be turned into executable tests. That is the most faithful implementation of Design Science Research: the artifact is not judged by elegance but by whether it prevents the failures it exists to prevent. The reproducibility sources also strongly support this posture, because they repeatedly identify hidden variability, underreporting, and non-comparability as central causes of bad conclusions. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search14ţłéturn6search2ţłéturn6search18ţłü

The table below answers the adversarial questions directly.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q50** How do we catch ÔÇťagent claims success from intentionÔÇŁ? | `run.end` must require observed status and actual outputs; evidence can only cite `completed` observed runs. |
| **Q51** How do we catch ÔÇťagent cites planned run as evidenceÔÇŁ? | The CLI should reject any evidence citation whose run status is not `completed`, with a specific invariant like `PLANNED_RUN_NOT_EVIDENCE`. |
| **Q52** How do we catch cherry-picking? | `audit` should group sibling runs by protocol + snapshot family + comparator and flag claims that cite only a favorable subset without a declared `selection_rule`. |
| **Q53** What if agent edits code after a run and before evidence classification? | If the run has a valid snapshot, the run remains valid and evidence references that snapshot; if no snapshot exists, the evidence should be invalid or capped. |
| **Q54** What if a human bypasses the agent? | Direct CLI use is fine; invariants still hold. Bypassing both agent and CLI by editing the store should be detectable via append-only logs or signatures. |
| **Q55** What if the agent repeats the same experiment and picks the better result? | Group runs by protocol/snapshot/resource signature and require either an explicit selection rule or aggregate reporting across sibling runs. |

Testing MLSpec itself should happen at three levels.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q65** How do we test MLSpec itself? | With adversarial fixtures that attempt to produce unsupported evidence or decisions. |
| **Q66** What is the test strategy? | Unit tests for grading/invariants, property tests for state transitions, integration tests for end-to-end stories, and golden transcript tests for agent skill behavior. |
| **Q67** Who runs the adversarial fixtures? | CI should always run them; humans and agents should also be able to run them locally. |

A good adversarial fixture pack should include at least:

- planned run cited as evidence
- failed run cited as success
- wrong split matched as baseline
- evaluator script drift hidden under same metric name
- underpowered run promoted to decision-grade
- single lucky run cherry-picked from siblings
- dirty workspace without snapshot
- after-the-fact brownfield import that tries to invent dataset lineage
- decision issued without claim
- code edited after evidence-bearing run and current workspace mistakenly treated as the run context

Operationally, MLSpec should ship first as a **package plus `mlspec init`**. That makes the installation and upgrade story answerable without requiring a huge platform.

| Question | Recommended implementation answer |
|---|---|
| **Q68** What does ÔÇťinstall MLSpec into a projectÔÇŁ mean? | Install the package, run `mlspec init`, create `.mlspec/`, configure adapters, and optionally install agent skill files/templates. |
| **Q69** Is there an `mlspec init` command? | Yes. It should scaffold config, store, sample skills/contracts, and basic ignore/projection files. |
| **Q70** Upgrade story? | Version the schema and run store migrations; version skills separately from schema. |
| **Q71** Is there a Web UI? | Not required for MVP. A read-only dashboard can come later, but agent/chat + CLI is enough initially. |
| **Q72** Multi-user story? | Start with single-writer local SQLite; add optimistic concurrency or server-backed storage later if teams need concurrent writes. |
| **Q73** Cloud execution story? | MLSpec remains the control plane. Runs may execute locally or remotely through adapters; authoritative state still flows through the CLI/store. |
| **Q74** Secrets and credentials? | Yes, they matter. MLSpec should store references to secret sources, never the secrets themselves. Use host env vars or secret managers. |

The most sensible first implementation sequence is therefore short:

1. Implement the typed store and the eight CLI groups.
2. Add snapshotting, evidence grading, and audit before building fancy integrations.
3. Add one chat-facing planner skill and three leaf skills: `frame_case`, `patch_code`, `run_candidate`.
4. Add the adversarial fixture pack and CI gating.
5. Only then add MLflow import and status projections, followed by Kubeflow import if needed.

That ordering is the best match to the source-implied risk profile: provenance, lifecycle, and validity come first; orchestration breadth comes later. ţłÇciteţłéturn1search0ţłéturn1search14ţłéturn0search2ţłéturn0search19ţłü

If you want the shortest practical reading path while implementing, start with ţłÇurlţłéPROV-DMţłéturn1search0ţłü, then ţłÇurlţłéCMMN specificationţłéturn0search5ţłü, then ţłÇurlţłéMLflow Tracking docsţłéturn0search2ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéMLflow System Metrics docsţłéturn22search0ţłü, then ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow Pipelines docsţłéturn0search19ţłü and ţłÇurlţłéKubeflow ML Metadata docsţłéturn13search0ţłü, then ţłÇurlţłéVisTrailsţłéturn1search1ţłü, ţłÇurlţłéPROV-AGENTţłéturn2search0ţłü, ţłÇurlţłéDesign Science in Information Systems Researchţłéturn1search14ţłü, and ţłÇurlţłéMachine Learning Reproducibility Checklist v2.0ţłéturn6search2ţłü. Those are the sources with the highest implementation leverage for the design you are actually trying to build.</implementation></ideaollogy>
<external-docs><opencode><command-docs>Commands
Create custom commands for repetitive tasks.

Custom commands let you specify a prompt you want to run when that command is executed in the TUI.

/my-command

Custom commands are in addition to the built-in commands like /init, /undo, /redo, /share, /help. Learn more.

Create command files
Create markdown files in the commands/ directory to define custom commands.

Create .opencode/commands/test.md:

.opencode/commands/test.md
---
description: Run tests with coverage
agent: build
model: anthropic/claude-3-5-sonnet-20241022
---

Run the full test suite with coverage report and show any failures.
Focus on the failing tests and suggest fixes.

The frontmatter defines command properties. The content becomes the template.

Use the command by typing / followed by the command name.

"/test"

Configure
You can add custom commands through the OpenCode config or by creating markdown files in the commands/ directory.

JSON
Use the command option in your OpenCode config:

opencode.jsonc
{
  "$schema": "https://opencode.ai/config.json",
  "command": {
    // This becomes the name of the command
    "test": {
      // This is the prompt that will be sent to the LLM
      "template": "Run the full test suite with coverage report and show any failures.\nFocus on the failing tests and suggest fixes.",
      // This is shown as the description in the TUI
      "description": "Run tests with coverage",
      "agent": "build",
      "model": "anthropic/claude-3-5-sonnet-20241022"
    }
  }
}

Now you can run this command in the TUI:

/test

Markdown
You can also define commands using markdown files. Place them in:

Global: ~/.config/opencode/commands/
Per-project: .opencode/commands/
~/.config/opencode/commands/test.md
---
description: Run tests with coverage
agent: build
model: anthropic/claude-3-5-sonnet-20241022
---

Run the full test suite with coverage report and show any failures.
Focus on the failing tests and suggest fixes.

The markdown file name becomes the command name. For example, test.md lets you run:

/test

Prompt config
The prompts for the custom commands support several special placeholders and syntax.

Arguments
Pass arguments to commands using the $ARGUMENTS placeholder.

.opencode/commands/component.md
---
description: Create a new component
---

Create a new React component named $ARGUMENTS with TypeScript support.
Include proper typing and basic structure.

Run the command with arguments:

/component Button

And $ARGUMENTS will be replaced with Button.

You can also access individual arguments using positional parameters:

$1 - First argument
$2 - Second argument
$3 - Third argument
And so onÔÇŽ
For example:

.opencode/commands/create-file.md
---
description: Create a new file with content
---

Create a file named $1 in the directory $2
with the following content: $3

Run the command:

/create-file config.json src "{ \"key\": \"value\" }"

This replaces:

$1 with config.json
$2 with src
$3 with { "key": "value" }
Shell output
Use !command to inject bash command output into your prompt.

For example, to create a custom command that analyzes test coverage:

.opencode/commands/analyze-coverage.md
---
description: Analyze test coverage
---

Here are the current test results:
!`npm test`

Based on these results, suggest improvements to increase coverage.

Or to review recent changes:

.opencode/commands/review-changes.md
---
description: Review recent changes
---

Recent git commits:
!`git log --oneline -10`

Review these changes and suggest any improvements.

Commands run in your projectÔÇÖs root directory and their output becomes part of the prompt.

File references
Include files in your command using @ followed by the filename.

.opencode/commands/review-component.md
---
description: Review component
---

Review the component in @src/components/Button.tsx.
Check for performance issues and suggest improvements.

The file content gets included in the prompt automatically.

Options
LetÔÇÖs look at the configuration options in detail.

Template
The template option defines the prompt that will be sent to the LLM when the command is executed.

opencode.json
{
  "command": {
    "test": {
      "template": "Run the full test suite with coverage report and show any failures.\nFocus on the failing tests and suggest fixes."
    }
  }
}

This is a required config option.

Description
Use the description option to provide a brief description of what the command does.

opencode.json
{
  "command": {
    "test": {
      "description": "Run tests with coverage"
    }
  }
}

This is shown as the description in the TUI when you type in the command.

Agent
Use the agent config to optionally specify which agent should execute this command. If this is a subagent the command will trigger a subagent invocation by default. To disable this behavior, set subtask to false.

opencode.json
{
  "command": {
    "review": {
      "agent": "plan"
    }
  }
}

This is an optional config option. If not specified, defaults to your current agent.

Subtask
Use the subtask boolean to force the command to trigger a subagent invocation. This is useful if you want the command to not pollute your primary context and will force the agent to act as a subagent, even if mode is set to primary on the agent configuration.

opencode.json
{
  "command": {
    "analyze": {
      "subtask": true
    }
  }
}

This is an optional config option.

Model
Use the model config to override the default model for this command.

opencode.json
{
  "command": {
    "analyze": {
      "model": "anthropic/claude-3-5-sonnet-20241022"
    }
  }
}

This is an optional config option.

Built-in
opencode includes several built-in commands like /init, /undo, /redo, /share, /help; learn more.

Note

Custom commands can override built-in commands.

If you define a custom command with the same name, it will override the built-in command.

</command-docs><skill-docs>Agent Skills
Define reusable behavior via SKILL.md definitions

Agent skills let OpenCode discover reusable instructions from your repo or home directory. Skills are loaded on-demand via the native skill toolÔÇöagents see available skills and can load the full content when needed.

Place files
Create one folder per skill name and put a SKILL.md inside it. OpenCode searches these locations:

Project config: .opencode/skills/<name>/SKILL.md
Global config: ~/.config/opencode/skills/<name>/SKILL.md
Project Claude-compatible: .claude/skills/<name>/SKILL.md
Global Claude-compatible: ~/.claude/skills/<name>/SKILL.md
Project agent-compatible: .agents/skills/<name>/SKILL.md
Global agent-compatible: ~/.agents/skills/<name>/SKILL.md
Understand discovery
For project-local paths, OpenCode walks up from your current working directory until it reaches the git worktree. It loads any matching skills/*/SKILL.md in .opencode/ and any matching .claude/skills/*/SKILL.md or .agents/skills/*/SKILL.md along the way.

Global definitions are also loaded from ~/.config/opencode/skills/*/SKILL.md, ~/.claude/skills/*/SKILL.md, and ~/.agents/skills/*/SKILL.md.

Write frontmatter
Each SKILL.md must start with YAML frontmatter. Only these fields are recognized:

name (required)
description (required)
license (optional)
compatibility (optional)
metadata (optional, string-to-string map)
Unknown frontmatter fields are ignored.

Validate names
name must:

Be 1ÔÇô64 characters
Be lowercase alphanumeric with single hyphen separators
Not start or end with -
Not contain consecutive --
Match the directory name that contains SKILL.md
Equivalent regex:

^[a-z0-9]+(-[a-z0-9]+)*$

Follow length rules
description must be 1-1024 characters. Keep it specific enough for the agent to choose correctly.

Use an example
Create .opencode/skills/git-release/SKILL.md like this:

---
name: git-release
description: Create consistent releases and changelogs
license: MIT
compatibility: opencode
metadata:
  audience: maintainers
  workflow: github
---

## What I do

- Draft release notes from merged PRs
- Propose a version bump
- Provide a copy-pasteable `gh release create` command

## When to use me

Use this when you are preparing a tagged release.
Ask clarifying questions if the target versioning scheme is unclear.

Recognize tool description
OpenCode lists available skills in the skill tool description. Each entry includes the skill name and description:

<available_skills>
  <skill>
    <name>git-release</name>
    <description>Create consistent releases and changelogs</description>
  </skill>
</available_skills>

The agent loads a skill by calling the tool:

skill({ name: "git-release" })

Configure permissions
Control which skills agents can access using pattern-based permissions in opencode.json:

{
  "permission": {
    "skill": {
      "*": "allow",
      "pr-review": "allow",
      "internal-*": "deny",
      "experimental-*": "ask"
    }
  }
}

Permission	Behavior
allow	Skill loads immediately
deny	Skill hidden from agent, access rejected
ask	User prompted for approval before loading
Patterns support wildcards: internal-* matches internal-docs, internal-tools, etc.

Override per agent
Give specific agents different permissions than the global defaults.

For custom agents (in agent frontmatter):

---
permission:
  skill:
    "documents-*": "allow"
---

For built-in agents (in opencode.json):

{
  "agent": {
    "plan": {
      "permission": {
        "skill": {
          "internal-*": "allow"
        }
      }
    }
  }
}

Disable the skill tool
Completely disable skills for agents that shouldnÔÇÖt use them:

For custom agents:

---
tools:
  skill: false
---

For built-in agents:

{
  "agent": {
    "plan": {
      "tools": {
        "skill": false
      }
    }
  }
}

When disabled, the <available_skills> section is omitted entirely.

Troubleshoot loading
If a skill does not show up:

Verify SKILL.md is spelled in all caps
Check that frontmatter includes name and description
Ensure skill names are unique across all locations
Check permissionsÔÇöskills with deny are hidden from agents</skill-docs>></opencode></external-docs>r
